<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Words, In Some Order]]></title>
  <link href="http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-11T09:15:27-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Westley Hennigh]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[WestleyArgentum@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ode to the Guy Sitting Across From Me Eating a Granola Bar and Looking Skeptically at My Bottle of Soylent]]></title>
    <link href="http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2015/01/10/ode-to-the-guy-sitting-across-from-me-eating-a-granola-bar-and-looking-skeptically-at-my-bottle-of-soylent/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-10T11:38:39-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2015/01/10/ode-to-the-guy-sitting-across-from-me-eating-a-granola-bar-and-looking-skeptically-at-my-bottle-of-soylent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We should be friends, you and I</p>

<p>but instead there’s distrust.</p>

<p>So we sit across this aisle</p>

<p>eating different things mushed.</p>

<br>


<p>I’d argue mines healthier.</p>

<p>You’d swear yours tastes better.</p>

<p>Anyway, shouldn’t we both be trying to murder the guy eating that delicious smelling, cholesterol-packed, egg-and-cheese sandwich?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Someone Get the President a Computer]]></title>
    <link href="http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2015/01/08/someone-get-the-president-a-computer/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-08T20:08:24-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2015/01/08/someone-get-the-president-a-computer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/extended_mind.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>There is profound truth in this bit of humor, but it seems not to have reached contenders in presidential debates.</p>

<p>For some reason, debates are treated like games of sport. Players win by blood and sweat alone. In the same way you don’t get to pro ball by controlling a robotic pitcher during tryouts, you can’t bring an iPad with you to a presidential debate (<a href="http://www.scribd.com/doc/110073567/The-2012-Debates-Memorandum-of-Understanding-Between-the-Obama-and-Romney-Campaigns">it’s actually against the rules</a>).</p>

<p>But while a ban on machines makes sense in the context of playing baseball, the same logic doesn’t hold when your goal is to govern effectively. More than that, those rules actually hurt the quality of debates by pushing candidates to rely on ill-conceived anecdotes and “he said”, “she said” arguments.</p>

<p>Give them computers, and let them cite the studies that support their ideas. Then let their opponents pull up those studies and call bullshit when they see who funded them. I’m more interested in who can quickly verify or refute information than I am in who can convey a more touching story about how the “American way” is in trouble.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rewards Programs and Gamification in Practice]]></title>
    <link href="http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2014/12/28/rewards-programs/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-28T20:28:53-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2014/12/28/rewards-programs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Credit card rewards programs are arguably the most successful, widest &ldquo;played&rdquo; examples of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamification">gamification</a> &mdash; a term with different connotations depending on who you talk to. I&rsquo;m someone who wants to believe in the power of games to do more than entertain, but in this system I’m tremendously disappointed.</p>

<p>Credit card companies make money in part by charging transaction fees whenever customers swipe their cards. These fees are paid by the merchant but are ultimately worked into the price of everything people buy.</p>

<p>In return for spending money, customers receive “points” that can be redeemed for products through the credit card company. Essentially, the price of everything people purchase is increased slightly, the card companies collect that money, and then card holders are able to pick out things their creditor was able to procure on discount. And different cards come with different schemes for awarding points, so the “savvy” consumer can spend hours devising strategies for spending.</p>

<p>This is a terrible game.</p>

<p>By lumping the cost of future purchases into current spending, people are effectively compelled to continue consuming. And by making credit card providers gatekeepers, they’re able to control what people purchase and skim money off for themselves.</p>

<p>Worst of all, there isn’t a way to opt-out. Merchants don’t offer different prices based on whether customers pay with cash or credit (this became <a href="https://www.paymentcardsettlement.com/en">legally possible</a> only in 2013, and visa encourages retailers to <a href="http://usa.visa.com/download/merchants/surcharge-considerations-and-requirements.pdf">maintain the status-quo</a>), so any money someone spends without getting points is a windfall for card companies. The Federal Reserve even <a href="http://www.bostonfed.org/economic/ppdp/2010/ppdp1003.htm">published a study</a> that found these programs resulted in a “nontrivial transfer” from cash-spending to credit card using, and consequently poor to rich, households.</p>

<p>So while I’d love to end this by saying “the only winning move is not to play”, even that won&rsquo;t work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Complex Government]]></title>
    <link href="http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2014/12/15/complex-government/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-15T21:30:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2014/12/15/complex-government</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not against &ldquo;Big Government&rdquo;, and frankly, I don&rsquo;t think you are either. Even the most extreme of us (that still believe in some form of governed society) expect the government to protect us from physical threats to our safety, and that alone makes it massive. Unfortunately, it also leads to systems that no single person can understand, and <em>that&rsquo;s</em> the real problem.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m against <em>complex</em> government. The complexity of our laws and institutions allows things to hide, costs us as taxpayers, and ultimately undermines confidence in our shared institutions.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/113/hr83">spending bill</a> that just passed the house and senate was fought over by people concerned with &ldquo;Big Government&rdquo;, and consequently does nothing to address complexity. Buried in its 1603 pages are all manner of arcane clauses. There&rsquo;s a finance provision, forged by lawyers for Citigroup, designed to cut the bindings that Dodd-Frank (itself impossible to understand) was supposed to create. And possibly more insidious, a section slipped into the back of the bill increases the amount of influence wealthy individuals can have by bumping up certain campaign contribution limits tenfold.</p>

<p>The concrete effects of these clauses will be extremely difficult to measure, in no small part because the systems they modify are already complicated and riddled with loopholes. But that &ndash; ironically &ndash; makes the broader implications clear. The special interests and lawmakers writing these laws have no interest in clarity or transparency, and so there won’t be any. Wealthy individuals will discreetly wield even greater influence, large financial institutions will make risky bets at taxpayer expense, and the other groups that got something appended to this bill will take their money and leave us with a more complicated, less efficient system. And if that’s not a recipe for disillusionment, I don’t know what is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Genetic Algorithms to Break Things]]></title>
    <link href="http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2014/05/18/using-genetic-algorithms-to-break-things/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-18T19:11:55-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2014/05/18/using-genetic-algorithms-to-break-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Few topics have the power to capture the imaginations of computer science undergrads like machine learning. And for many of us, genetic algorithms in particular hold seemingly infinite promise. During your first year or two at school you&rsquo;re on the verge of solving all of the worlds problems using creatures pulled from your mind and made real by your trusty computer.</p>

<p>But then reality sets in, and we become jaded. The awesome AI in the game you&rsquo;re making -that was going to learn to walk, run, and ultimately outpace the player- just keeps finding physics bugs and getting stuck in walls. And the bots you wrote to manage a simulated hedge fund keep triggering massive selloffs and bringing down the whole virtual economy.</p>

<p>By the time we leave school we&rsquo;ve given up on genetic algorithms. &ldquo;Cute,&rdquo; we say, &ldquo;but too opaque and unwieldy to be used in the real world.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Well, maybe our little creatures don&rsquo;t do what we want. Maybe they just like to misbehave &ndash; and maybe that&rsquo;s ok. By embracing the stochastic nature of genetic algorithms we can turn them into some of the best validation tools we have. Let loose, these algorithms might try things that would never occur to us humans, and they might expose terrible bugs along the way.</p>

<p>So instead of trying to cultivate an AI just like a human player, try changing your fitness function to reward something odd, like collision with walls. And maybe bots that make a bunch of money are overrated, perhaps there&rsquo;s something interesting to be learned from bots that try to cause massive market fluctuations.</p>

<p>I think the real promise of genetic algorithms is in breaking things, not in playing nicely within their virtual boxes.</p>

<hr />

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in genetic algorithms and <a href="http://julialang.org/">Julia</a>, check out <a href="https://github.com/forio/GeneticAlgorithms.jl">GeneticAlgorithms.jl</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lumberjack.jl: Lets Talk About Logging in Models]]></title>
    <link href="http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2014/01/24/lumberjack-talking-about-logging-in-models/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T14:51:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://WestleyArgentum.github.io/blog/2014/01/24/lumberjack-talking-about-logging-in-models</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Evan Miller <a href="http://www.evanmiller.org/why-im-betting-on-julia.html">made an interesting observation in his blog recently</a>: “[Julia is] poised to do for technical computing what Node.js is doing for web development — getting disparate groups of programmers to code in the same language.” Well, I agree, and I might take it further. I’d like to see scientists and modelers come together with server-side developers to talk about logging&hellip; <a href="http://forio.com/blog/lumberjack-talking-about-logging-in-models/">(contiue reading)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
